Now, since this is TEDGlobal,
الآن، وبِما أنّنا في مؤتمر تيد العالمي،
who can tell me what this is called in French?
من يستطيع أن يقول لي ماذا نُسمّي هذا باللّغة الفرنسيّة؟
I see you're all up on the history of hurdy-gurdy --
أرى أن لكم جميعا ما تقولون عن تاريخ الأورغن اليدوي.
"vielle à roue."
"فيال آرو".
And in Spanish, "zanfona."
وباللغة الاسبانية ، "زَنْفُونيا".
And in Italian, "ghironda," okay?
وبالإيطالية ، "جيروندا"، حسنا؟
Hurdy-gurdy, or wheel fiddle.
أورغن يدوي، أو كمان ذو عجلة.
So, these are the different kinds and shapes of the hurdy-gurdy.
لذلك، هنالك أنواع وأشكال مختلفة من الأورغن اليدوي.
The hurdy-gurdy is the only musical instrument
والأورغن اليدوي هو الآلة الموسيقية الوحيدة
that uses a crank to turn a wheel
التي تستخدم ذراع تدوير لتحريك عجلة
to rub strings, like the bow of a violin,
تقوم بدورها بفرك السّلاسل، تماما مثل قوس الكمان،
to produce music.
لإنتاج الموسيقى.
It has three different kinds of strings.
إنّ له ثلاثة أنواع مختلفة من السّلاسل.
The first string is the drone string,
السّلسلة الأولى هي سلسلة الدّندنة،
which plays a continuous sound like the bagpipe.
وهي التي تُصدر صوتا مستمرّا مثل مزمار القربة.
The second string is a melody string,
السّلسلة الثّانية هي سلسلة اللّحن،
which is played with a wooden keyboard tuned like a piano.
والتي يتمّ التحكّم فيها بلوحة مفاتيح خشبية تُضْبط مثل البيانو.
And the third string is pretty innovative.
والثالث هو مبتكر جدا.
It's also the only instrument
إنّه أيضا الآلة الوحيدة
that uses this kind of technique.
التي تستخدم هذا النوع من التقنية.
It activates what's called the buzzing bridge, or the dog.
إنّه يقوم بتشغيل ما يسمى الجسر الطنّان، أو الكلب.
When I turn the crank and I apply pressure,
عندما أقوم بتحريك ذراع التّدوير و إحداث ضغط
it makes a sound like a barking dog.
فإنّه يُصدر صوتا مثل نُباح الكلب، حسنا؟
So all of this is pretty innovative,
وهذا مُبتكر جدا،
if you consider
إذا أخذنا بعين الإعتبار
that the hurdy-gurdy appeared about a thousand years ago
أنّ الأورغن اليدوي ظهر منذ نحو ألف سنة مضت،
and it took two people to play it;
وإستلزم الأمر شخصين للعزف عليها،
one to turn the crank,
أحدهم لتحريك ذراع التدوير،
and another person -- yes -- to play the melody
وشخص آخر، نعم، لعزف اللّحن
by physically pulling up large wooden pegs.
وذلك بالقيام بسحب أوتاد خشبية كبيرة يدويّا.
Luckily, all of this changed a couple of centuries later.
لحسن الحظ، تغيّر هذا بعد مُضيّ عدّة قرون.
So, one person could actually play
لذلك، حاليّا يُمكن لشَخص واحد العزف عليها
and almost -- this is pretty heavy --
وتقريبا -- وهو ثقيل جدا --
carry the hurdy-gurdy.
حَمْل الأورغن اليدويّ.
The hurdy-gurdy has been used, historically, through the centuries
وأُسْتخدم الأورغن اليدوي، تاريخيا ، على مرّ القرون
in mostly dance music
في أغلب موسيقى الرّقص،
because of the uniqueness of the melody
بسبب الطّابع الفريد للنّغم
combined with the acoustic boombox here.
جنبا إلى جنب مع الصندوق الصوتي هنا.
And today, the hurdy-gurdy is used in all sorts of music --
واليوم، يتم استخدام الأورغن اليدويّ في جميع أنواع الموسيقى --
traditional folk music,
الموسيقى الشعبيّة التقليديّة،
dance, contemporary
والرّقص، والموسيقى
and world music --
المعاصرة والعالميّة --
in the U.K., in France, in Spain
في بريطانيا، في فرنسا، في إسبانيا
and in Italy.
وفي ايطاليا.
And this kind of hurdy-gurdy takes anywhere from three to five years [to order and receive it].
وهذا النوع من الأورغن اليدوي يستغرق الحصول عليها من 3 إلى 5 سنوات.
It's made by specialized luthiers,
وهو مصنوع من قِبَل صنّاع متخصّصين،
also in Europe.
في أوروبا أيضا.
And it's very difficult to tune.
ومن الصّعب جدّا ضَبْطُهُ.
So without further ado, would you like to hear it?
لذلك، ومن دون أن نكثر من الكلام، هل تودّون سماعه؟
(Audience: Yes.)
(الجمهور : نعم.)
Caroline Phillips: I didn't hear you. Would you like to hear it? (Audience: Yes!)
كارولين فيليبس : لم أسمع جيّدا. هل تودّون سماعه؟ (الجمهور : نعم!)
CP: Okay.
كارولين فيليبس : حسنا.
There I go.
فلنبدأ.
I'd like to sing in Basque,
حسنا، أريد أن أغني بلغة الباسك،
which is the language spoken in the Basque Country where I live,
وهي اللّغة المَحْكيّة في بلاد الباسك حيث أسكن،
in the region in France and Spain.
إنّها منطقة في فرنسا وإسبانيا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
[Basque]
[الباسك]
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is a song that I wrote
قُمْت بتأليف هذه الأغنية
based on traditional Basque rhythms.
بناءا على إيقاعات الباسك التقليدية.
And this is a song that has a kind of a Celtic feel.
وهي أغنية فيها نوع من الشّعور السِّلتيكي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Thank you. Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)